<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A brief enquiry into the grounds and reasons, whereupon the infallibility of the Pope and the Church of Rome is said to be founded by Edward Bagshawe ...</title>
            <author>Bagshaw, Edward, 1629-1671.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1662</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 105 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29039</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B404</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9275</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11906333</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11906333</idno>
            <idno type="VID">50685</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29039)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 50685)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 51:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A brief enquiry into the grounds and reasons, whereupon the infallibility of the Pope and the Church of Rome is said to be founded by Edward Bagshawe ...</title>
                  <author>Bagshaw, Edward, 1629-1671.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[20], 35 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A.M. ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1662.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in University of Chicago Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Infallibility.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Doctrines.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Protestant authors.</term>
               <term>Popes --  Infallibility.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:50685:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50685:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Brief ENQUIRY INTO THE Grounds and Reaſons, Whereupon the INFALLIBILITY OF THE POPE and CHVRCH OF ROME Is ſaid to be Founded.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Edward Bagſhawe</hi> St. of <hi>Ch. Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Luk. 19.</hi>
                  </bibl> Why do you not of your ſelves judge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> is right?</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Eph. 5.</hi>
                  </bibl> Let no Man deceive you with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> words.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>A.M.</hi> and are to be ſold by the Book <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:50685:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50685:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable the Earl of <hi>ANGLESEY,</hi> one of his Majeſties moſt Honourable Privy Councell.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Believe your Lordſhip in your <hi>Search</hi> and Survey of the Myſteries of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, with which you entertain your Privacy, have often with great amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment conſidered, how many ſtrange and admirable Effects, do daily pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from ſmall and ignoble Cauſes; for not only <hi>Thunder, Rain, Lightning,</hi> and other com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon <hi>Phaenomena,</hi> which do aſtoniſh the World, have their whole Make and Compoſition, from a ſeemingly caſuall and undeſigned Concourſe, of Light and Fleeting Clouds; but likewiſe largeſt Rivers are fed by ſecret and conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Springs; and the World it ſelf, if traced and reſolved into its moſt viſible Originall, is framed of <hi>Atomes;</hi> and the <hi>Earth,</hi> which is vulgarly conceived to be the Baſis and Center of the Univerſe, <hi>is,</hi> as God himſelf is pleaſed
<pb facs="tcp:50685:3"/>to expreſs it, <hi>hung upon Nothing;</hi> and yet, by that Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty Hand which fixed it, it is made ſtable and firm enough, to endure unmoved all that Hurry and Variety of Mutation, wherewith the rolling Motion of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, do daily threaten it.</p>
            <p>What wonder your Lordſhips Contemplation, hath begot in viewing the <hi>Works of Nature,</hi> I doubt not but hath been continued, when you deſcended from them to behold the <hi>Works of Art;</hi> eſpecially the Civil Policies of States and Kingdomes; in which, as your Lordſhip hath been alwayes moſt knowingly converſant, ſo you can from the deepeſt and beſt grounded Experience evince, that though Earthly Empires, (I mean ſuch as are not guided by Chriſtian and truly-Religious Principles) have an Outward Semblance of a Subſtantiall and Laſting Greatneſs, yet the Baſis which doth ſupport the whole Politicall Frame, is but ſome State-trick or other, ſome little Expedients found out to amuſe the Vulgar, whoſe Folly muſt be pleaſed, or elſe they will never be go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned.</p>
            <p>But how far the Wit of man, can advance it ſelf, to imitate the Works of God, even thoſe of a Creative Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, the making <hi>Something out of Nothing,</hi> is in no Policy more diſcernible, than in that deep and wiſe contrivance of ſubtle men, the <hi>Papacy;</hi> the Body of which hath a pleaſing Aſpect, and is ſet out with a very ſpecious Gloſs; all the Parts do ſeem extreamly well-proportioned; there is a ſtrange Linking and Confederacy of all its Principles; and to the Eye of a Superficiall Beholder, it preſents no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but a beautifull and comely Outſide. But if any be ſo curious, as to look beyond its Varniſh and firſt Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance; ſhould we pry into the Foundation of this
<pb facs="tcp:50685:3"/>Goodly Structure, we ſhall find it, like the <hi>Iſland of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los,</hi> alwayes <hi>Floating;</hi> or rather, like the Earth, to <hi>hang upon nothing;</hi> For the <hi>Pope's Infallibility,</hi> or the <hi>Churches Authority,</hi> or ſome ſuch fond <hi>Chimera,</hi> is all the Baſis which doth under-prop this Building. Things that are ſo confidently aſſerted, and yet upon triall ſo ſhamefully begged, that were not the world, in <hi>Gods juſt Judgement,</hi> given over to a vicious and Lazy Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulity, all that is built upon ſuch thin and empty Fallacies would not ſubſiſt one moment; but for the preſent, the Arts of planting a devout Ignorance, have ſo farre prevailed, that the world doth hugge its Bondage; and men finding a great deal of eaſe in being quietly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, they are content to <hi>worſhip the Beaſt,</hi> and are an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry that any ſhould fright them from embracing a Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which hath made the way to Heaven ſo very plaine and eaſie, that, whatſoever becomes of the <hi>Seeing,</hi> they that are <hi>Blind</hi> enough ſhall be ſure never to miſſe of it.</p>
            <p>It is now, <hi>My Lord,</hi> ſome ſcores of Yeares ſince we of this Nation have by Scripture-Light diſcovered all the Frauds and Cheats of this <hi>Miſtery of Iniquity;</hi> and yet it ſeems all mens eyes are not opened, for ſome of late have pleaded for <hi>Popery,</hi> and for that which is the chief Bulwark of it, the <hi>Popes Authority,</hi> with as good a grace (if Railing and needleſſe Rhetorick may deſerve that name) as if they had never been anſwered.
<note place="margin">Ruſhworth <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al.</hi> 1.</note> One in his great heat of <hi>zeal,</hi> or ſomething worth, doth tell us, <hi>That Queſtions about the Popes Authority o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Biſhops, of Biſhops over Prieſts, and of Prieſts o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Laity, are of no ſmall moment. But he that goes about to destroy this Hierarchy, aimeth at nothing leſse then an Utter overthrow of Religion.</hi> Which are but
<pb facs="tcp:50685:4"/>
               <hi>Bellarmines</hi> words in Engliſh,
<note place="margin">Bellar. <hi>Praef.</hi>
               </note> and, if in ſtead of the word <hi>Religion</hi> they had ſaid <hi>Popery,</hi> they had ſpoke nothing but the Truth, ſince that is bottomed onely in the <hi>Popes Authority.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Fiat Lux</hi>—de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated to the Counteſs of <hi>Arundell,</hi> and twice Printed.</note> Which a late nameleſſe Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor ſo farre cryes up, that he ventures to ſpeake words, which no ſober man would owne. <hi>In my Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>Chriſt our Lord hath no leſſe ſhowne his Divinity and Power, in the Pope, than in himſelf.</hi> And again, <hi>All things conſidered I may truly ſay that Chriſt in the Pope and Church,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 376, 377, &amp;c.</note> is more miraculous than in his own Perſon.</hi> And yet farther, as if thoſe expreſſions were too modeſt Blaſphemy, and not barefaced enough, he goes on, <hi>The firſt great Fundamentall of Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, which is the Truth and Divinity of Chriſt, had it not been for the Pope, had failed long agoe in the world.</hi> Whereupon enlarging himſelfe, he addes <hi>whence I may truly ſay, that</hi> Chriſt is the Popes God, <hi>for if the Pope had not been, and proved ſo reſolute an Aſſertour, Chriſt had not been taken for any ſuch perſon as he is believed this day.</hi> And ſo in a boaſte concludes, <hi>This I will boldly ſay and am aſſured of, that if the</hi> Pope <hi>be not an</hi> Unerring Guide <hi>in affaires of Religion, all is loſt. For a man once rid of the Controll of his Authority, may as eaſily deride and as ſolidly confute the</hi> Incarnation, as the ſprinkling of Holy-water, <hi>nor could the reaſon of the world confute them.</hi> While I relate ſuch kind of Paſſages as theſe which I tremble to mention, I hope your Lordſhip will pardon my zeal, if I complaine a little, that Treatiſes of a farre more innocent Nature, are ſharply cenſured, while theſe open Impieties doe ſcape unpuniſhed; as if our Lawes were keen onely againſt the Aſſerters of <hi>Chriſtian Liberty,</hi> but had no edge at all againſt the
<pb facs="tcp:50685:4"/>Broachers of <hi>Antichriſtian Blaſphemy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Since then the <hi>Pope's Infallibility,</hi> is that <hi>Name of Blaſphemy,</hi> which makes all its Patrons ſo bold and Irreligious; ſince that is <hi>the Bottomleſſe Pit,</hi> out of which all this <hi>Deadly ſmoke</hi> doth iſſue: I have here, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to your Lordſhips commands, endeavoured to ſhow the Vanity and Ridiculouſneſſe, as well as Impiety of that opinion. In which if I have not anſwered your Lordſhips expectation, as to the exactneſſe of my ſtile and ſtrict manner of my Reaſoning, I ſhall not wonder: ſince no Induſtry of mine can be ſufficient to ſatisfie your Lordſhips accurate and unequalled ability in Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: But if I have ſhowed my diligence, and left no Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument unanſwered, how plainly and inelegantly ſoever, I hope then your Lordſhip will let my willingneſſe to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey, compound for the failings in my Obedience; ſince, if the Enemy be killed, it is all one, as to the truth of the Victory, whether it was done by a <hi>Rough Stone,</hi> or by a <hi>Poliſhed Sword;</hi> nor was <hi>David</hi>'s conqueſt the leſſe eſteemed, becauſe he vanquiſhed <hi>Goliah</hi> onely with a <hi>ſling.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, <hi>My Lord,</hi> before I conclude, I ſhould crave leave to tell the world, how <hi>Good,</hi> as well as how <hi>Great,</hi> you are. I ſhould borrow ſo much Language from <hi>Common Fame,</hi> and the <hi>Generall Voice</hi> as to declare that for Wiſdome, to Direct; for Eloquence, to Expreſſe; for Diligence, to Execute; very few equall, and none exceed your Lordſhip. But ſince what is truth in it ſelf, and would be Juſtice in others, in me, becauſe of my Relation, may be eſteemed flattery; I ſhall turne my <hi>Praiſes</hi> of, into <hi>Prayers</hi> for you, that your Lordſhip may be alwayes fixed upon the <hi>Rocke of Ages,</hi> and in
<pb facs="tcp:50685:5"/>all your walkings acknowledg that God, who onely is <hi>Infallible;</hi> That Chriſtianity may ever ſteere your actions, and all your other Politicall and Morall excellencies may ſtill vail and doe Homage unto a knowing Piety; that with your truly Religious and Excellent Lady, together with your moſt Hopefull and Virtuous Children, you may be long preſerved a <hi>Good</hi> and <hi>Great Example,</hi> is and ſhall be the conſtant Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute> 
               <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt Obliged and moſt Obedient Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant and Chaplain <hi>Edward Bagſhawe.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>Drury-Lane <date>
                     <hi>April</hi> 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. 1662.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:50685:5"/>
            <head>The Preface.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here are none who allow themſelves any liberty of Enquiry, ſo little skilled in the Controverſies and Diſputes between the Papiſts and Us, but muſt needs perceive, that when they are driven out of all the Subterfuges and little Policies (which they call <hi>Diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi>) by which they labour to defend their Errours, then their laſt reſort is, to the <hi>Infallibility of their Church;</hi> which as they handle it, is a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a Plaiſter large and broad enough, though not to cure, yet to palliate and hide their noiſome and diſeaſed Doctrines. And therefore unleſs we can take from them this Refuge alſo, it will be to as little purpoſe to combate their other Tenets, how falſe and erroneous ſoever, as it was for <hi>Hercules</hi> in the Fable, to wreſtle with <hi>Anteus;</hi> who as often as be was thrown down upon his Mother the Earth, roſe up again with new and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubled vigour: So till we are able by plain force of Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to convince the Papiſts of their folly, in believing that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, their <hi>Mother,</hi> the <hi>Churches Infallibility,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:50685:6"/>no induſtry can be ſo quick in cutting off and destroying their Errours, as that pregnant and fruitfull womb will be, in conceiving and bringing them forth again. As they tell us, that young Vipers when they are aſſaulted, run into their Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers mouth, and from thence ſeek ſhelter in the poiſonous womb that bare them; ſo all thoſe Prodigies, rather than Opinions of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation, Supererogation, Image-Adoration,</hi> and the like, when they are purſued home, and preſſed beyond the ſtrength and ſupport of their own proper Principles; then to defend themſelves, they take Sanctuary in <hi>Infallibility,</hi> and under the protection of that, they lye, though not concealed from the eye, yet ſafe from the edge of their oppoſers. For to inſtance in the vaſt uſe of it, what if all the ſenſes we have, and the Apoſtle too, do aſſure us that the <hi>Bread</hi> in the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> even after Conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, remains true and reall <hi>Bread</hi> ſtill, yet if that <hi>Church,</hi> whoſe judgement is ſuppoſed to be <hi>Infallible,</hi> tells us there is no ſuch matter, but that under that Form, whatever we think, there is contained our Lord <hi>Chriſt</hi> both in his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine and Humane Nature, we must then in ſpite of all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction, either believe her, or elſe vindicate our ſelves from ſo unreaſonable and ſo abſurd an opinion, by diſprov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her <hi>Infallibility.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Leaving therefore other parts of the Romiſh Religion, which are either bold additions to the Word of God, or elſe ſo groſs falſifications of it, that they deſerve not a particular confutation, I have here endeavoured to ſet upon that <hi>Man of ſin,</hi> where his ſtrength lyes, ſince by our Saviours exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>to break the Serpents head,</hi> is not only the most rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy way to diſpatch him, but the moſt ſafe way too to prevent any infection by his venome.</p>
            <p>In proſecution of this Deſign, that I might not out of too much eagerneſs and heat miſtake my Adverſary, I took this Method.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb facs="tcp:50685:6"/> 
               <hi>1.</hi> I laboured fully to inform my ſelf of the <hi>Church of Romes</hi> Doctrine, eſpecially in thoſe points, wherein we as <hi>Proteſtants</hi> do differ from them. And this I did, not by ſtudying the Collections of others, or by adhering to ſome one Author of their Party, whoſe Writings they are not bound univerſally to own, but by diligent peruſing the <hi>Canons</hi> of their moſt magnified <hi>Councels,</hi> particularly that of <hi>Trent,</hi> which I read only in ſuch Editions, as are approved and atteſted by themſelves.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> Since the <hi>Popes Infallibility,</hi> how tamely ſoever our Modern Papiſts ſwallow it, was anciently a great Diſpute amongſt them, and in the Schools among their learned men is not yet decided: ſome attributing it to the <hi>Pope</hi> (which ſeems to have been the judgement of the <hi>Junto</hi> at <hi>Trent</hi>) others preferring a <hi>Councell,</hi> of which opinion were the two Councels of <hi>Baſil</hi> and <hi>Conſtance,</hi> as appears in their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees yet extant. Hereupon I carefully peruſed Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine</hi> upon this Subject, who is the Popes Principall, and moſt avowed, I will adde, and most learned Champion. And becauſe I think he hath ſpoke fully the ſenſe of the <hi>Court of Rome,</hi> and left nothing unſaid which might juſtifie his Cauſe, I made it my buſineſs in the following Treatiſe to anſwer his Arguments.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> Though they inferre it from different Principles, yet ſince both Papiſts and Proteſtants do agree in this Concluſion, that <hi>the Scripture is the undoubted Word of God,</hi> I have from that Armory fetched all my weapons, by which I fight against this Monſter of <hi>Infallibility:</hi> for ſince <hi>Bellarmines</hi> beſt plea for it is from ſome few Texts, by him miſerably wreſted and miſtaken, I thought it my duty to take this <hi>ſword of the Spirit</hi> out of that <hi>Gollans</hi> hand, and not only ſonite off his head with it, but likewiſe uſe it my ſelf thronghout my whole Diſcourſe. For though the Papiſts are ſo bold as to
<pb facs="tcp:50685:7"/>deny the Scriptures to be a <hi>Sufficient</hi> Rule, yet for ſo much as there is of them, they dare not deny them to be Infallible: and therefore</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Whatever Teſtimonies I might have alleadged, either in behalf of the Scriptures Sufficiency and Divine Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therity, or againſt the perpetuall <hi>Infallibility</hi> of any man, or number of men whatever, (of which kind of Citations I have collected many, and obſerved more in the ancient Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, eſpecially before <hi>Conſtantines</hi> time) yet I purpoſely omitted them, becauſe <hi>1.</hi> In Queſtions, wherein the Right of any thing is controverted, to call in Witneſſes is altogether impertinent. <hi>2.</hi> No Authority of man ought to prevail, unleſs it hath the Authority of God, and the conſent of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, <hi>i.e.</hi> Scripture or Right Reaſon to back it. <hi>3.</hi> Many Writers of our own, as Mounſieur <hi>Daillee, Chillingworth,</hi> the Lord <hi>Falkland,</hi> the Lord <hi>Digby,</hi> now Earl of <hi>Briſtow,</hi> &amp;c. have already ſhewed the vanity and uſeleſneſs of ſuch Allegations: and becauſe it is poſſible that the example of the laſt Honourable Perſon I named, may be urged againſt me, ſince his preſent practice doth contradict his former principles; I will only adde this, that ſince his Book is not yet anſwered by himſelf, I hope he thinks it unanſwerable, and will not long continue in communion with that Church, whoſe Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons he hath ſo well overthrown. <hi>4.</hi> This way of writing by Quotations, makes every Controverſie uncertain, dilatory, and endleſs: for as the poſſeſſed perſon ſaid to the <hi>Exorciſts, Jeſus I know, and Paul I know, but who are ye?</hi> ſo may the common Reader ſay of Authorities and Fathers, <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture</hi> I know, and <hi>Reaſon</hi> I know, but who are ye? for any farther than they ſpeak according to the Dictates of the two former, theſe latter must not be heard, much leſs believed or followed.</p>
            <p>That this little Treatiſe, thus curtailed of all Authorities,
<pb facs="tcp:50685:7"/>and deplumed of thoſe Sentences from Fathers (with which others do not think they ſtuff, but rather adorn their Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings) is like to be little read, and leſs eſteemed by the men of a contrary perſwaſion, I eaſily foreſee; but yet the Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is ſo very uſefull, that I could not omit to handle it. For</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> If it ſhall appear, that the <hi>Church and Pope of Rome</hi> are not <hi>Infallible,</hi> then I hope all thoſe who have unwarily embraced their Errours, upon the account of their unerring Authority, will be induced to ſhake off their lazineſs, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs themſelves ſtrictly to enquire into the Grounds of what they Believe; and according to the advice of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> (who was undoubtedly <hi>Infallible</hi> in that direction) <hi>Prove all things, and</hi> then <hi>hold faſt that which is good.</hi> The greateſt Truth, while it is untried, may for ought we know be an Errour; and all that while if we entertain it, we fall upon our Religion onely by chance; and ſerve God, as the <hi>Samaritans</hi> did, for which our Saviour blames them, <hi>we know not why.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> If the <hi>Pope and Church of Rome</hi> be not <hi>Infallible</hi> in their Judgment about Religious matters, then it follows, that they ought not to impoſe upon the Judgment of others; there being nothing more unreaſonable then this, that they ſhould <hi>Lord it over the Faith,</hi> or, <hi>Conſciencious Perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> of other men, who are not certain but they may Erre and be deceived themſelves.</p>
            <p>This laſt Conſideration, how far it may be improved, to moderate the great Fierceneſſe and Rigor of too many among our ſelves (who in things of ſo poore, ſo triviall, ſo need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe and ſo unmanly a nature, will have their will to be a Law) I mention only, it being too ſad a Theme to inſiſt long upon. But if Religion, which is in it ſelfe the firmeſt lye; if the Law of Chriſt, which is a Law of Love; cannot make us agree and live together as Brethren, yet let feare of the
<pb facs="tcp:50685:8"/>common Enemy, prevent our ſeparation. When <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Lot</hi> fell out about their Paſtures (and I wiſh much of our Church-quarells now were not of the ſame nature) the ſpirit of God remarks upon it, <hi>the Canaanits and the Periz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zites were then in the Land.</hi> Hereby intimating, that it was a moſt unſeaſonable time for them to diſagree and to divide from each other in, when they were ſurrounded in the midſt of Enemies. This paſſage perfectly agrees with our Caſe, and on the very ſame motive beſpeakes a mutuall Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concilement; for certainly <hi>the Canaanites are in the Land,</hi> the <hi>Philiſtines are,</hi> if not <hi>upon,</hi> yet <hi>Among</hi> us, who watch our Halting, and hate <hi>Conformiſts</hi> and <hi>Non-conformiſts</hi> (if theſe muſt be once more the Unhappy Termes to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh us) both alike; the one they hate for going ſo farre from, the other, for not comming neerer to them. If God in juſt Judgment upon our unchriſtian Animoſities, ſhould make us a Prey to thoſe Incircumciſed <hi>Philiſtines, Polyphemus</hi> courteſie to <hi>Uliſſes,</hi> of devouring him laſt, would be the greateſt favour that he can expect, whoever he be that is now most eager in denying his weake, but yet Chriſtian Brother, that Liberty which he thinks Chriſt hath purchaſed; and none but <hi>Antichriſt</hi> will ſeeke utterly to bereave us of. Should we ever fall into the Papiſts hands again I cannot expect they ſhould uſe us more mildly, then their predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours did <hi>Samſon, i.e.</hi> put out our eyes, and make us grind in their Mills, Or as they afterwards ſerved the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> take away our Weapows of Warre; our <hi>Scripture,</hi> and the best, if not the onely Interpreter of it, <hi>Enligtned Reaſon;</hi> and ſo leave us Naked and Defenceleſſe, to the Aſſaules of <hi>Ignorance</hi> firſt, and if that will not prevaile, to the Fury of a Mercileſse <hi>Inquiſition.</hi> Which laſt, will be found the ſtrongeſt and moſt forcible Engine, rather then Argument, by which they defend their <hi>Infallibillity.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:50685:8"/>
            <p> But how ill an opinion ſoever I have both of the Papiſts Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and of the unchriſtian wayes they take to propagate it, yet farre be it from me to wiſh, that amongſt us they may ſuffer the ſame hard meaſure, which I know by their principles, they are alwayes ready to inflict. For ſo much doe I deſire their Converſion (which can never be ſincere un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it be voluntary and unconſtrained) and ſo little feare their Power of ſeducing (ſince their greateſt ſtrength lies in the Ignorance of their followers, rather then in the cunning of their Guides) that I heartily wiſh all Penall Lawes againſt them were utterly taken away: For I never yet ſaw any Argument that could clearly evince, why any ſort of men, who would profeſſe a peaceable ſubjection unto the Civill Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, might not in all their Civill Rights, be protect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by it.</p>
            <p>I must confeſs there are two things, which do much diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence the caſe of the Papists, from that of any other Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Sect this day in the World, and which renders the tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of them very unſafe, if not unwarrantable. One is, their depending upon, and owning of a forreign Power, and that ſuch a Power too, which according to the Opinion of their Teachers, can when he pleaſeth diſpenſe with them for, and releaſe them from their moſt ſacred Engagements, ſo that a State can have no ſecurity, but that whenever they have opportunity, they will endeavour a Change;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 5. <hi>de Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tif. Rom. c.</hi> 7. <hi>Quod ſi Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ani non depoſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erunt</hi> Neronem <hi>&amp; ſimiles, id fuit quia dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant vires tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porales, nam a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lioqui jure id poter ant face<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re,</hi> &amp;c.</note> and their preſent peaceableneſs may justly be attributed meerly to their want of ſtrength: which <hi>Bellarmine</hi> is not aſhamed to ſay, was the ſole cauſe why the Primitive Chriſtians were coment to ſuffer without Reſiſtance: from which Poſition what can follow, but that it concerns the wiſdome and policy of every State, to keep thoſe under, whom as to tempor all Subjection, it cannot confide in. But could our <hi>Papiſts</hi> in <hi>England</hi> give ſufficient evidence of their hearty diſowning ſuch an irreligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb facs="tcp:50685:9"/>Tenet, yet there is another thing practiſed by them, which makes it highly queſtionable whether a Kingdome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing Chriſtianity ought to tolerate them in, and that is their <hi>Worſhip of Images,</hi> which is a ſinne ſo contrary to the expreſs letter of the divine Law, and ſo repugnant to the common ſenſe and reaſon of all ſober men, that God puniſhed it ſeverely even in the Heathen <hi>Caldeans,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 50.38.</note> as well as in his own people the Jews. But bating theſe two indefenſible Crimes, rather than Errours, their other opinions of <hi>Merit, Purgatory, Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> &amp;c. may for ought I ſee be charitably born with, ſince in themſelves they create no prejudice to the publick Peace, which even Chriſtian Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, ſo far as they are Magiſtrates, ought principally, if not ſolely, to provide for.</p>
            <p>If any think that ſuch Indulgence, like warm Aire, will ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen theſe monſtrous Births too faſt, and prove the ready way to encreaſe Popery, they are utterly ignorant either how that Religion firſt began, or by what Arts it is still upheld. For till the world was aſleepe in ſenſuality, and blinded with Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, the Enemy could not ſow theſe Tares; and had they not afterwards maintained by force, what they gained by fraud, thoſe Tares could never have proſpered into ſo large an Harveſt. In oppoſition, therefore to that conſpiracy of Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and Malice, which goes to compound the Roman Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion I ſhall not ſcruple to ſay, that if his <hi>Majeſty</hi> (whom God, I doubt not, hath deſigned for ſome ſuch great and gener<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous worke, as now I mention) be pleaſed ſtill to continue to countenance the free Preaching and Reading of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and to diſalow the impoſing of any thing, which either is contrary to or beſides it; It will then be as impoſſible for Popery to prevail, as for duſt to reſiſt the Wind, or for Airy Clouds to Eclipſe the Sun. The Errors of Popery, for want of Divine Warrant, have in them ſuch a Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall
<pb facs="tcp:50685:9"/>and Inherent weakneſſe, that unleſſe they are upheld by a Coercive power, they will ſinke and fall of themſelves; as thinne and emty vapours, if they have but roome enough in the Aire, will diſperſe themſelves, without the help of any wind to ſcatter them. To en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour therefore the weakning of Popery, by any thing which looks like Perſecution, doth indeed give it ſtrength and Reputation, as if it had reaſon on its ſide and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſtood in need of force to ſuppreſſe it. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides it onely fills the Church with <hi>Hypocrites</hi> inſteed of <hi>Converts;</hi> who by mingling with, and masking them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves under the Name of Proteſtants, doe what they can ſecretly to diſpirit and undermine our Religion, the power of which they never felt, ſince they were onely frighted to the Embracing of it.</p>
            <p>But perhaps I need not plead ſo zealouſly for the not perſecuting of <hi>Popery,</hi> when too many of our unwary Gentry begin already to be taken with the outward Pompe of it; and ſome that yet profeſse themſelves to be of our Church, and thoſe of good Note too, are not afraid to plead for ſomething more then its <hi>Toleration.</hi>
               <note place="margin">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Thorndike.</hi> Juſt Weights and Meaſures.</note> Since by telling us in Print, that the <hi>Pope is not Anti-chriſt;</hi> that <hi>Papiſts are not Idolaters;</hi> nay by affirming, that <hi>All are Schiſmatickes, who upon that ſcore do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe Communion with them.</hi> They not onely ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh the Virtue and Piety of our firſt Reformers) who all built upon that Foundation, but likewiſe ſhow how willing they are upon any Termes how wretched and unworthy ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, to returne into <hi>Egypt,</hi> and bring us to our <hi>Bricke</hi> and <hi>Bondage</hi> again. If this be not the intent of ſome I cannot imagine what meanes the crying up of that great <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ana</hi> of the Papiſts, <hi>the Churches Authority,</hi> and making that the <hi>ſole Interpreter of Scripture.</hi> The Preaching up
<pb facs="tcp:50685:10"/>of <hi>Lent,</hi>
               <note place="margin">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Gunning</hi> upon Mat. 9. the Lent Faſt. —<hi>Eliz.</hi> 5. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Thorndike. ut ſuprà.</hi>
               </note> and other Politicall Fiſh-dayes, as <hi>Religious Faſts,</hi> and <hi>of Apoſtolicall Inſtitution,</hi> quite contrary both to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe Scripture and an <hi>Act of Parliament.</hi> The inſinuating that <hi>we may Lawfully pray for the Dead,</hi> and likwiſe <hi>expect ſome benefit by their Prayers,</hi> which in time may eaſily be improved to our Praying unto them. Theſe with ſome other Opinions of the like nature, ſo farre degenerating from our <hi>Primitive Proteſtancy,</hi> doe ſhow that if the Age is willing to be deceived, there are not wanting Learned men, who are willing enough to deceive them.</p>
            <p>The deſigne therefore of this ſmall Treatiſe, is not only to depoſe the <hi>Pope</hi> from his uſurped Title of <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibility,</hi> but to keep all perſons elſe, whether <hi>Churches,</hi> or <hi>Church Rulers,</hi> from taking the Chaire and ſucceeding into his room. For ſince our Lord <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath given every Believer, Reaſon to judge with, and a Rule to judge by: ſince over and above he hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed <hi>his ſpirit to all that ask it,</hi> which ſerves to aſſiſt the one, and to explain the other; he hath there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by appointed every man, in matters of Faith and God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, to be a Judge for himſelf, though not of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And he who uſeth thoſe meanes which our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour hath left, and ſeekes to him in them, may In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly be aſſured, that though in ſome things he may Erre, as a man, yet he ſhall never finally miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Whereas he that leanes upon a Church, of what denomination ſoever, cannot be ſure that he ſhall not be deceived: ſince any number of men, are as fallible in their Judgement as one (eſpecially when they are all ſworne, as in the Papacy, to uphold the Authority, and to defend the dictates of one) This conſideration alone will I hope prevaile with all Impartiall and diſintereſſed per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb facs="tcp:50685:10"/>to take the ſafeſt ſide, and with <hi>David,</hi> to chuſe <hi>to fall into the hands of God,</hi> whoſe word duely ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into never deceived any, rather then <hi>to fall into the hands of men,</hi> who being Blind themſelves, do firſt take care to Blind their Followers and then <hi>lead them into a Ditch.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Edward Bagſhaw.</signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Drury-Lane,</hi> 
                  <date>Aprill <hi>16. 1662.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:50685:11"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:50685:11"/>
            <head>THE GREAT QUESTION ABOUT The Infallibility of the Pope AND Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">Queſt.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Whether there be any ſufficient Ground from Scripture or Reaſon, to believe the Pope and Church of</hi> Rome <hi>to be Infallible?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or the better underſtanding, and clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſtating of this Great Queſtion, I will premiſe theſe three things;</p>
            <p n="1">1. By the <hi>Pope,</hi> I mean the <hi>Biſhop of Rome,</hi> not in his <hi>Perſonall capacity,</hi> as he is <hi>a Man</hi> (for ſo, the prodigious and monſtrous Lives of many of their Popes, which are
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:50685:12"/>obvious in Story,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Multi Pontifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces fuerunt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> probi.</hi> Bell. <hi>Prafat.</hi>
               </note> cannot but force them to acknowledge, that he is liable to Errour) but in his <hi>Politicall,</hi> or, which is all one, his <hi>Eccleſiaſticall</hi> capacity; as he is the pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Head of the Church;</hi> and veſted with all thoſe Immuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Priviledges, which his Favourers ſuppoſe to be due unto the <hi>Univerſall Biſhop.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. By <hi>the Church of Rome,</hi> I mean, not the diffuſed and ſcattered Body of the Papiſts, but, according to their own Senſe, how Abſurd and Inſignificant ſoever, the <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Doctours of their Church,</hi> aſſembled together in a <hi>Councell;</hi> where, they may be ſuppoſed to meet, with the greateſt Advantage and Opportunity, for the Diſquiſition and Search of Truth.</p>
            <p n="3">3. By <hi>Infallible,</hi> I mean, to have a certain, fixed, and unerring Judgement in Religious matters; which things alone do properly belong to the determination and cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance of a <hi>Church,</hi> as it is a <hi>Church.</hi> And, in this ſenſe of the Queſtion, thus explained, in as great a Latitude as any Papiſt can poſſibly underſtand it in, I deny the <hi>Pope,</hi> whether conſidered as apart from, or conjoyned with, as a part of, a <hi>Councell,</hi> to be <hi>Infallible.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the proof of which Aſſertion, though I might find out great variety of Arguments, from the expreſs and direct contradictions which have been among the Popes themſelves, ſome reverſing that which others have ratifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and others eſtabliſhing that, which their Predeceſſors under the ſevereſt Penalties have forbid. Yet ſince the proper and direct way of Arguing, lyes in ſhewing the weakneſs and inſufficiency of thoſe Arguments, which are brought in defence of the Popes Infallibility, that is the Method which I purpoſe altogether to inſiſt on. For ſince this great and ſo much admired <hi>Diana</hi> of the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> is no <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>i. e.</hi> a thing to be diſcerned by its own
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:50685:12"/>Light, and to be credited meerly for it ſelf; as the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of the Spirit is, when it bears witneſs unto the truth of Scripture; and beſides, it being generally denied by all the Proteſtants, who make the Errours of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> the ground of their ſeparation from them, hence it cannot be expected, that we ſhould tamely give up out Aſſent to believe this <hi>Infallibility,</hi> unleſs there be ſome evident and concluding Reaſons to enforce it from us. If therefore it ſhall appear, that whatever <hi>Bellarmine</hi> (and when I mention him, I mean the ſtrength of the whole Popiſh Party) hath ſaid, is altogether impertinent and unconcluding, indeed nothing elſe but a plain begging the thing in Queſtion; my Deduction from thence will be <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible,</hi> viz. that we have as yet no Reaſon to believe the <hi>Popes Infallibility.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To clear up this, the beſt way will be to take a ſhort view, of thoſe Arguments which <hi>Bellarmine</hi> alleadgeth, in his Books <hi>De Pontifice Romano;</hi> and they are briefly theſe three.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Some Texts of Scripture in the New Teſtament.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Some Analogicall Inferences out of the Old.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Some Abſurdities and Inconveniences which would follow in the Church of God, ſhould we not allow the <hi>Pope</hi> and <hi>Church of Rome to be Infallible.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The Texts of Scripture which <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> and all Writers ſince him, do urge to prove the <hi>Popes Infallibility</hi> by; are theſe three, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.18, 19. <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.31, 32. <hi>Job.</hi> 21.15, 17. From which they draw theſe three Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. 1. That in thoſe fore-mentioned places, our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour did confer upon <hi>Peter</hi> ſome ſpeciall Priviledges, above and beyond the reſt of the Apoſtles; and they were 1. <hi>Supremacy,</hi> in <hi>Matthew.</hi> 2. <hi>Infallibility</hi> in <hi>Luke.</hi> 3. <hi>Univerſall Epiſcopacy</hi> in <hi>John.</hi> 2. They Aſſume,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:50685:13"/>that whatever was beſtowed upon <hi>Peter,</hi> was not confined unto his Perſon, but was promiſed likewiſe unto his Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours: ſince what was granted unto <hi>Peter,</hi> was given for the good of the Church, and therefore ought not to die with him. 3. They take for granted, that the <hi>Pope</hi> was <hi>Peter</hi>'s Succeſſour, both in the <hi>Biſhoprick</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in all his other <hi>Priviledges;</hi> and for the laſt, they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadge nothing but the credit of that, which they call, <hi>Apoſtolicall Tradition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whether or no theſe Deductions are cleare in the Texts, or violently haled and wreſted from them; with ſo much impudent and ſhameleſſe Sophiſtry, as a wiſe and diſintereſſed Perſon, would bluſh to be guilty of, will beſt appeare by examining the places themſelves; and if, when they are put upon the Racke, they can be forced to confeſſe ſo much, as <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> and the <hi>Popes</hi> Paraſites conclude from them; I ſhall then conſent to dethrone <hi>Scripture</hi> from its plainneſſe and Perſpicuity; but till then I muſt take leave to thinke, that that Church doth very wiſely, which makes <hi>Ignorance</hi> and <hi>Implicite Faith, the Mother of Devotion:</hi> for nothing leſſe then an over-awed and Religious ſtupidity, would make any man ſubmit unto ſuch Impoſſible and farre fetched interpretations.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The place in <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.18, 19. runs thus, <hi>And Jeſus anſwered and ſaid unto him,</hi> i. e. to <hi>Peter, Bleſſed art thou Simon Barjona, for fleſh and bloud hath not revealed this to thee, but my Father which is in Heaven: And I ſay alſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, that thou art Peter, and upon this Rock will I build my Church; and the gates of Hell ſhall not prevail againſt it: And I will give unto thee the Keyes of the Kingdome of Heaven; and, whatſoever thou ſhalt bind on earth, ſhall be bound in Heaven; and whatſoever thou ſhalt looſe on earth ſhall be looſed in Heaven.</hi> Which place they thus inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:50685:13"/>1. By the <hi>Rock,</hi> upon which Chriſt ſaith he <hi>will build his Church,</hi> is meant the Perſon of <hi>Peter;</hi> and the Churche's being built upon him, ſignifies, ſay they, that the care and government of it was committed to him; and thus they underſtand likewiſe his <hi>Having of the Keyes.</hi> 2. By the power of <hi>Binding and Looſing;</hi> they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, the power of commanding and puniſhing; of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and repealing Laws; with all ſuch things as belong to a Soveraign and Legiſlative Power. 3. They tell us, that whatever <hi>Peter</hi> had here, was likewiſe granted to the <hi>Pope,</hi> who is his Succeſſour; and therefore he being the <hi>Rock,</hi> and the <hi>Foundation</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> cannot be <hi>toſſed about with every wind of Doctrine,</hi> and therefore is <hi>Infallible.</hi> But I anſwer,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Upon ſuppoſition that <hi>Peter</hi> here was conſtituted, as they call him, <hi>Head and Prince of the Apoſtles;</hi> yet, how would this Perſonall Priviledge, any more belong to the <hi>Biſhop of Rome</hi> (if he were <hi>Peter</hi>'s Succeſſour) than what our Saviour elſewhere ſaith to <hi>Peter, Why didſt thou doubt, O thou of little faith!</hi> doth note the Pope's uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty and inſtability in Believing? Or,
<note place="margin">Mat. 14.31.</note> what our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our preſently after ſpeaks, <hi>Get thee behind me Satan!</hi> doth ſignifie, that every <hi>Pope</hi> is an <hi>Incarnate Devil;</hi> or, to take the mildeſt Interpretation, an <hi>Adverſary</hi> to Chriſt, and to the good of mankind? For what Reaſon can be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned, why the <hi>Pope</hi> may not as well ſucceed in <hi>Peter</hi>'s Perſonall Defects, as into his Priviledges? ſince the Scripture is utterly ſilent, either that he had, or that he was to have a Succeſſour in either? But</p>
            <p n="2">2. I deny the Suppoſition, upon which all this <hi>Babel</hi> is built; that our Saviour did confer any Preeminence of Power and Authority upon <hi>Peter,</hi> above the reſt of the Apoſtles; becauſe</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:50685:14"/> 1. Theſe words, <hi>Upon this Rock will I build my Church,</hi> cannot without blaſphemy, be affirmed of the Perſon of <hi>Peter;</hi> who himſelf was built upon the <hi>Rock, Christ;</hi> and was not the <hi>Foundation,</hi> but only a <hi>Workman</hi> at the Building. Indeed in the Figurative Deſcription of <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 21.14.</note> which <hi>John</hi> makes in his Viſion, he compares it to a City, which had <hi>twelve Foundations, upon which were written the Names of the twelve Apoſtles.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 21.</note> So that if the <hi>Papiſts</hi> will needs call <hi>Peter</hi> a <hi>Foundation,</hi> I hope they will take in the reſt of the Apoſtles, to be ſharers with him in that Title. But ſince the whole Deſcription in <hi>John,</hi> City and all, is only Figurative and Metaphoricall, the <hi>Foundation</hi> there mentioned, muſt be like the City; <hi>i. e.</hi> ſo called, not in a Reall, but only Metaphoricall Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception. For to ſpeak properly, as <hi>Paul</hi> doth, <hi>No other Foundation can any man lay,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.11.</note> than what is already laid, and that is,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 2.</note> that <hi>Jeſus is the Chriſt.</hi> And therefore when we are ſaid <hi>to be built upon the Foundation of the Prophets and Apoſtles;</hi> the meaning is not, that we are built upon their Perſons, but upon their Doctrine; the ſumme of which, is contained in <hi>Peter</hi>'s confeſſion; upon <hi>which Rock,</hi> our Saviour hath ſo built his Church, that <hi>the Gates</hi> or <hi>Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> of <hi>Hell,</hi> however they may rage, and ſtrive to ruine it; yet they ſhall never be able finally to prevail againſt it; but Chriſt will have a Church, in ſome place or other, unto the end of the world.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If <hi>Peter</hi> was the <hi>Rock,</hi> ſo as all Chriſtians, even the Apoſtles themſelves, were to depend upon his guidance; what a wretched and tottering condition would the Church have been in, when this <hi>Rock,</hi> ſo ſoon after was ſhaken, and almoſt removed out of his place? For within ſome few minutes, he is rebuked by our Saviour, in no milder language than this, <hi>Get thee behind me Satan!</hi> The Story
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:50685:14"/>of his denying, and that with Oaths, his Maſter, is too notorious to be palliated, and too ſad to be inſiſted on: Even after our Saviours <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> when they pretend this promiſe of <hi>Infallibility</hi> was inſeparably annexed to him,
<note place="margin">Act. 10.</note> we find him unreſolved in that part of his Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which concerned his <hi>preaching the Goſpel unto the Gent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iles;</hi> and therefore had the aſſiſtance of a particular <hi>Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> more fully to inform him of it; and afterwards at <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch,</hi> we read that he was of ſo inconſtant and unequall a carriage, in that great point of <hi>Chriſtian Liberty,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying herein more than he ought,
<note place="margin">Gal. 2.</note> with the Jewiſh rigour and auſterity, that <hi>Paul</hi> was forced <hi>openly to reprove him</hi> for it, and ſo prevent the contagion of his ill example. So that if he, who in the <hi>Court of Rome</hi>'s ſtile, is called <hi>Prince of the Apoſtles,</hi> in matters of ſo great moment, was thus ſubject to Errour and Fallibility, I wonder with what face, the <hi>Pope,</hi> upon the account of being <hi>Peter</hi>'s Suceeſſour, can plead any exemption.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Theſe words, <hi>I will give unto thee the Keyes of the Kingdome of Heaven,</hi> do not denote any peculiar power, that <hi>Peter</hi> had over the reſt of the Apoſtles; for then, how came it to paſs afterwards, that there were ſo many, and ſo fierce contentions amongſt them, <hi>Who ſhould be greateſt?</hi> Which our Saviour, at two ſeverall times, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lences, not, by commanding them to obey <hi>Peter,</hi> as their <hi>Chief;</hi> but by utter prohibiting any deſire of Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty? If they anſwer us, as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> doth, that the Apoſtles did not clearly underſtand, that <hi>Peter</hi> was to be <hi>Supream Head,</hi> till after our Saviour's Reſurrection, (which by the way, is nothing elſe but a bold playing with ſacred Scripture) Then I demand farther, when there was a new Apoſtle to be choſen into the room of <hi>Judas,</hi> why did not <hi>Peter,</hi> by his ſole Authority,
<note place="margin">Act. 1.</note> deſign
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:50685:15"/>him? or at leaſt when the multitude of Diſciples (for ſo we read that all of them were concerned in the choice) <hi>had appointed two,</hi> why did they not preſent them both unto <hi>Peter,</hi> that he might chooſe one, rather than ſuffer the matter to be decided by <hi>Lot:</hi> ſure had <hi>Peter</hi> had any paramount and extraordinary Power, and withall a peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar <hi>infallible ſpirit,</hi> he could not have better exerted it, than in that emergency. For the <hi>Head of the Church,</hi> in ſo concerning a buſineſs, firſt to permit <hi>all the multitude,</hi> to have a voice in chooſing an Apoſtle, (for if our modern Arguments are good, he might juſtly fear, that they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the greateſt part unlearned, would chooſe one like themſelves, and ſo prejudice the reputation of Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Authority) and afterwards to leave the matter unto the uncertain caſualty of a Lot, whereas the choice ſeemed properly to belong to <hi>Peter</hi>'s Juriſdiction; this argues ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that his Power, or his care of the Church, was very little; of which laſt, I hope the Papiſts do not doubt; and therefore muſt needs deny the former. For what is it elſe but <hi>to tempt God,</hi> to have recourſe unto caſting of <hi>Lots,</hi> when a way of choice, more prudent and Infallible, by referring the buſineſs to <hi>Peter</hi>'s ſingle Deciſion, was opened for them. But it ſeemes the Apoſtles underſtood nothing of <hi>Peter</hi>'s <hi>Supremacy,</hi> either then, or afterwards, when they went to chooſe <hi>Deacons,</hi> which by all the <hi>Apoſtles, Peter</hi> not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo much as particularly mentioned, was committed to the <hi>Mulitude;</hi> and after the choice, <hi>Impoſition of hands</hi> was performed, not by <hi>Peter</hi> alone, but as the Text ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſely ſaies, by <hi>all the Apoſtles.</hi> Will they tell us, that this was a thing below him;
<note place="margin">Act. 6.</note> and that it did not become <hi>Peter</hi>'s Authority, to intereſſe himſelf in a matter of ſo petty concernment? This plea is taken from them, becauſe we read that <hi>the Twelve,</hi> and among them ſure <hi>Peter</hi> was
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:50685:15"/>one, did not think it below them: and beſides, it will appeare, a ſtrange kind of conceated and uſeleſſe Authority, which they aſcribe to <hi>Peter;</hi> which in maters, neither of the greateſt, ſuch as was the choice of an <hi>Apoſtle;</hi> nor of the leaſt moment, ſuch as was the choice of a <hi>Deacon,</hi> would ever ſo particularly exert it ſelf, that we might once take notice of his Prerogative. But what kind of Equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity <hi>Peter</hi> ſtood in to the reſt of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> he ſhewed,
<note place="margin">Act. 8.</note> in ſubmitting to be ſent with <hi>John,</hi> unto <hi>Samaria;</hi> to finiſh that worke of the Goſpell, which <hi>Philip</hi> had begun there; for ſure our Saviours Argument is <hi>Infallible,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh 15.</note> that <hi>He who is ſent, is not greater then he who ſends him.</hi> And it would have been a ſtrange boldneſſe (I believe the <hi>Pope</hi> would call it by a worſe name in his <hi>Cardinalls</hi>) ſhould the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> have thus preſumed to ſend their <hi>Prince,</hi> had he indeed been ſo conſtituted over them. Yet further, when there was a Queſtion ſtarted about the uſe of <hi>Jewiſh Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies,</hi> and a <hi>Synod</hi> convened about it,
<note place="margin">Act. 15.</note> why did not <hi>Peter</hi> then <hi>Preſide</hi> as chiefe? Why did he ſuffer the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to be diſputed, after he had declared his own Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? Why doth <hi>James,</hi> who ſpoke after him, give him no more Honourable ſtile, then plaine <hi>Simeon?</hi> and ſeemes himſelf, in ſaying <hi>My ſentence is,</hi> to give the whole ſolution of the Query, as alſo the Forme of the Future Decree, without taking any notice of <hi>Peter</hi>'s deciſion? Whence comes it, that after a ſtrict Debate, the reſult was in the Councell, <hi>It pleaſed the Apoſtles, and Elders with the whole Church;</hi> and the ſuperſcription of the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter runs, <hi>The Apoſtles and Elders and Brethren;</hi> and the decree, <hi>It ſeemed good to the Holy Ghoſt, and to us;</hi> without any mention of <hi>Peter</hi> at all, whoſe Supremacy and Infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, ought not to have been thus ſilently paſſed over, that the Churches afterwards, might know whether to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:50685:16"/>to have recourſe for ſatisfaction of their ſcruples. How comes it to paſſe, that we hear no Newes of <hi>Peter</hi> after, but the ſtory is continued wholy about <hi>Paul</hi> as if the <hi>Primacy</hi> had been transferred to him? ſure the Holy Penman, who mentions ſo many of <hi>Paul</hi>'s travells, that were of farre leſſe moment, would not have omitted <hi>Peter</hi>'s Journey to <hi>Rome,</hi> his ſitting <hi>Biſhop</hi> there for eighteen yeares, and fixing the <hi>Succeſſion,</hi> and <hi>Infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility</hi> to boot, upon that <hi>See,</hi> had he underſtood any thing of it. Afterwards when <hi>Paul</hi> meets <hi>Peter</hi> at <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>och,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 2.</note> Why did he not vaile to him, but Irreverently ſtand upon his Termes, and <hi>Openly reprove</hi> him? Laſtly, For Inſtances are infinite in this kind, why doth that bleſſed Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> himſelf,
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 5.</note> diſclaime any ſuch kind of Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, ſtiling himſelf <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a <hi>Fellow-Elder,</hi> and utterly forbiding any pretentions of <hi>Lordſhip</hi> and <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty</hi> even over the <hi>Flocks</hi> they fed, much more over their <hi>Fellow Miniſters.</hi> Certainly none of theſe things, can conſiſt with that grant, which <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> fondly ſuppoſeth, was here made to <hi>Peter,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we may juſtly conclude, that the words have ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Interpretation, which is plainly this: Our Saviour asking his Diſciples, what men thought of him, and whom they took him to be; after he had heard the various opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of others, he continues to aske them theirs; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon <hi>Peter,</hi> in the name of the reſt, replies <hi>thou art the Chriſt the Son of God;</hi> which being the Article, that then was oppugned, our Saviour pronounces him <hi>Bleſſed</hi> for it, not, as if other Believers were not equally bleſſed, and did not obtain this Faith by Revelation too (for ſo the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith expreſſely,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 12.</note> that <hi>none can call Jeſus Lord</hi> i. e. <hi>Chriſt, but by the Holy Spirit</hi>) but thoſe words are ſpoken excluſively, as to any outward meanes, whereby
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:50685:16"/>he might attain that knowledge. For that no leſſe pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, than the Imediate action of the Spirit of God, can make a man to Believe on Chriſt, is not onely evident from the nature of the thing, which exceeds all created ability; but likewiſe from thoſe perpetuall contradictions and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, which Beleivers themſelves have, before the Spirit of God hath explained and ſolved them. The promiſe therefore which our Saviour makes to <hi>Peter,</hi> of <hi>giving him the Keyes;</hi> &amp;c. concerned all the Apoſtles, ſince they were Believers and Diſciples as well as he; and ſo our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our enlarges it after his Reſurrection, in that generall Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, <hi>Whoſe ſins ſoever you retain they are retained</hi> i. e. By your Preaching, whom you doe declare to be under the power of ſin, if they <hi>Repent not and Believe the Goſpell,</hi> their <hi>ſins are retained.</hi> i. e. <hi>Bound</hi> and tied faſt to them, for God will never pardon ſuch; but others that embrace the Goſpell, are <hi>remitted</hi> i. e. looſed and abſolved. So that the reſult of all is this: From this place, cannot be inferred either. 1. That <hi>Peter is that Rocke, upon which Chriſt will build his Church;</hi> but rather, <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf confeſſed by <hi>Peter.</hi> Or 2. That <hi>Peter</hi> here had any Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eminence of <hi>Power, Authority</hi> and <hi>Infallibility,</hi> above the reſt of the Apoſtles; he receiving this Promiſe onely, as a Prolocutor of the Apoſtles, in whoſe names he ſpoke, and they being afterwards joyned all equally in the ſame Commiſſion. Much leſſe can it be deduced, 3. That the <hi>Pope,</hi> who is not once mentioned, was <hi>Peter</hi>'s Suceſſour, or hath the leaſt pretenſion to claime any thing from him, unleſſe it be his <hi>Errors</hi> and <hi>Fallibility.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond place of Scripture, which is brought for the Patronage of <hi>Peters</hi> firſt, and then of the <hi>Popes Infallibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;</hi> is that which if they had ſearched the whole Scripture, they could not have found one that doth more directly
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:50685:17"/>make againſt it: The place is <hi>Luc.</hi> 22.31, 32. <hi>Simon, Simon, behold Satan hath deſired to have you, that he may ſift you as Wheat: But I have prayed for thee, that thy Faith faile not; and when thou art converted ſtrengthen thy Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</hi> Here, though by a moſt miſerable inſtance, we find how fraile and fallible <hi>Peter</hi> was; yet <hi>Bellarmine</hi> draws from hence two priviledges, that were conferred upon <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> 1. That <hi>Peter</hi> might never fall from the Faith, how much ſoever he was tempted of the Divell. 2. That none of his Succeſſors ſhould ever teach any thing contrary to the truth. The Firſt of theſe I grant; and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that it was by virtue of this Prayer of our Saviours, that <hi>Peter</hi> recovered his ſtation again, after ſo great a ſhaking, but withall I adde, that this was no peculiar Priviledge to <hi>Peter,</hi> but in common to all the reſt, as is more cleare in <hi>Joh.</hi> 17. <hi>v.</hi> 9. and the Reaſon why <hi>Peter</hi> was particularly ſpoken to, was becauſe our Saviour fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaw he ſhould more foully miſcarry: and therefore ſtood in need of this Cordiall to relieve him. But the ſecond, is ſo little to be gathered from the Text <hi>viz,</hi> that the <hi>Pope,</hi> as <hi>Peter</hi>'s Succeſſor ſhould never teach falſe Doctrine, that it would be an extream vanity in me, to go about to confute it: Onely one fetch of <hi>Bellarmines</hi> is not to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted; when we object, that if this place be to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of <hi>Peter</hi>'s <hi>Succeſſors,</hi> then it muſt preſuppoſe, that all the <hi>Popes</hi> (who will needs intrude into that Title) muſt firſt deny <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and after that be <hi>converted,</hi> before they can <hi>ſtrengthen their Brethren,</hi> or be confirmed in the Faith themſelves. To this <hi>Bellarmine</hi> replies, that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> doth not ſignifie, <hi>Peters</hi> being <hi>turned</hi> from ſin; but his <hi>turning himſelf</hi> to the <hi>weak Brethren,</hi> to diſcourſe with them, which is a piece of ſo merry Sophiſtry, that it only ſerves to ſhow the wretched boldneſſe of Partiall
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:50685:17"/>and ſelf-deſigning men, when they make uſe of Scripture to ſhore up and to underprop their ill got greatneſſe; the plaineſt places then ſhall not eſcape their perverſe and irregular fancies; as this, wherein there is a gracious Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe made of <hi>Peters</hi> Recovery and Converſion, is made to ſignifie juſt nothing, but the Impiety of thoſe men, who dare thus abuſe it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Third and laſt place, which is urged in this Controverfie, and moſt inſiſted on, though to as little, or if poſſible, leſſe purpoſe, than either of the former; is <hi>Joh.</hi> 21.15, 17. Where our Saviour repeats no leſſe then three times. <hi>Peter feed my Lambes;</hi> and <hi>feed my ſheepe. Bellarmines</hi> Comment upon theſe words, is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry admirable. 1. By <hi>Feed,</hi> which in the Scripture dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect ſignifies only to <hi>Teach,</hi> and compaſſionatly to care for; he underſtands to Rule and Governe, as Prince, becauſe the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is ſometimes ſo rendered. 2. By <hi>Lambes</hi> and <hi>Sheepe,</hi> he ſayes are underſtood Chriſtians of all ſorts and ſizes. <hi>Lambes</hi> ſignifying the <hi>weak in Faith;</hi> and <hi>Sheep</hi> the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and <hi>Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> which are to other Chriſtians, as <hi>Sheep</hi> are to their <hi>Lambes,</hi> i. e. the bringers of them forth in the Faith of Chriſt; over whom <hi>Peter</hi> is here conſtituted <hi>Univerſall Biſhop,</hi> and none who belong to Chriſt, as one of his <hi>ſheep,</hi> but muſt by virtue of this Commiſſion, be obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient unto <hi>Peters</hi> Rule and Direction. Had <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> ſtopped here and ſtreined this Scripture no farther, he might have had ſome commendation for his Wit, though very little for his Honeſty, but when he goes on, and Infers, 3. That whatever here is granted to <hi>Peter,</hi> was entended likewiſe for his Succeſſour; and 4. That the Biſhop af <hi>Rome</hi> did ſucceed him: I cannot but obſerve how ill an Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Scripture, Prejudice and Prepoſſeſſion is; for who that reads this place without looking upon it, through
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:50685:18"/>the Spectacles of the <hi>Popes Infallibility,</hi> can make any other ſenſe of it, than this; that <hi>Peter</hi> having denyed our Saviour <hi>thrice,</hi> is here <hi>thrice</hi> minded of his Duty, to humble him under the ſenſe of his former miſcarriage, and to direct him, that he could not better demonſtrate his Love to Chriſt, then by ſhowing a care over his little ones; which our Saviour had before enjoyned him, when he ſaid <hi>Thou being converted, confirme thy Brethren;</hi> which is all one with what is here commanded him, <hi>Feed my Lambs and Sheep:</hi> i. e. Teach, Inſtruct, Reprove, exhort them, and therein performe all the Acts of a Faithfull Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter; as <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Elders</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Epheſus;</hi> bids them <hi>to Feed the Church of God;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 20.28.</note> and <hi>Peter</hi> to the <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> of the Believing Jewes, in that very place, where he forbids them all manner of Soveraignty and Coercive Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction, commands them to <hi>Feed the Flock of God,</hi> which was among them.
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 5..2</note> And what the word <hi>Feed</hi> ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies, God himſelf hath already explained, when he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes by his Prophet, that he would give unto his People, <hi>Paſtours according to his own heart, who ſhould Feed his people,
<note place="margin">Jer. 3.13.</note> with knowledge and with underſtanding.</hi> So that the word cannot be rendred to <hi>Rule and Governe with Force and Authority,</hi> and <hi>making all men ſubmit, unto his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Dictates;</hi> for this is that which God condemnes in the Shepheards of <hi>Iſrael; who ruled over them with ſeverity,
<note place="margin">Ezek. 33.4.</note> and with Rigour, and Cruelty;</hi> but with all gentleneſſe and condeſcenſion to accommodate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves unto the weak and infirme ſtate of their Flockes;
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 40.11.</note> as God deſcribes himſelf. <hi>He ſhall Feed his Flocke like a Shepheard, he ſhall gather the Lambes with his Arme, and ſhall gently lead thoſe that are with Young.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 34.15.16</note> And again I <hi>will Feed my Flock, and cauſe them to lye down; I will ſeek that which was loſt, and bring again that which was driven away, and will bind up that which was broken, and will ſtrengthen
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:50685:18"/>that which was ſicke.</hi> This is the part of a good Shepheard, and this is the ſumme of what here is enjoyned <hi>Peter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After this plain and clear vindication of theſe Scriptures, had I a mind to make my ſelf, and my Reader ſport; I could not find a better Subject, than by enlarging and deſcanting upon thoſe excellent Arguments, that <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> alleadges to prove. 1. That <hi>Peter</hi> was <hi>Biſhop of Rome;</hi> and 2. That the <hi>Pope</hi> did ſucceed him, not only into that <hi>Biſhoprick,</hi> but likewiſe into all his other more than Apoſtolicall Priviledges. The firſt he proves, <hi>from the dignity of that See, which,</hi> ſayes he, <hi>could no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ariſe, but becauſe</hi> Peter <hi>was Primate there:</hi> but who doth not ſee, that the dignity of it, might eaſily ariſe from other cauſes, as particularly from this, becauſe it was the chief ſeat of the <hi>Roman Empire;</hi> which is the Reaſon aſſigned, why the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Conſtantinaple</hi> was to have the ſecond place,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Concil. Constan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinop. Can.</hi> 5.</note> becauſe he was Biſhop of <hi>New-Rome.</hi> 2. He proves it, becauſe <hi>Peter died and was bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried there, as,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>is apparent from his Sepulchre, yet to be ſeen.</hi> As if it was not as eaſie for the Popes to make ſpecious Tombs, for men who never died in <hi>Rome,</hi> as to <hi>Canonize,</hi> and make prayers to <hi>Saints,</hi> who, it is to be feared, have no place in Heaven. His Reaſons to defend the <hi>Pope</hi>'s ſucceſſion unto <hi>Peter,</hi> are of the ſame nature; as 1. <hi>Becauſe</hi> Peter <hi>ought to have a Succeſſour; there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>as much reaſon for an Univerſall Biſhop, now, as then.</hi> Which I eaſily grant, and return it thus, But there was no Reaſon for an <hi>Univerſall Biſhop</hi> then; for then ſure the holy men, whoſe buſineſs it was to write all things abſolutely neceſſary unto faith, and godlineſs, would not have omitted a matter ſo very important, unto the peace and unity of Chriſtians; and therefore we may ſafely conclude, there was no ſuch <hi>Univerſall Biſhop;</hi> but
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:50685:19"/>admitting it were ſo, how will it appear, that the <hi>Biſhop of Rome,</hi> more than any other <hi>Biſhop,</hi> was to be his Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour? <hi>Yes,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bellarmine.</hi> 2. <hi>None ever did yet pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to be</hi> Peter<hi>'s Succeſſour, but only the Biſhop of Rome, and therefore undoubtedly he was the man;</hi> Which is all one, as if an Uſurper, who had gained a Crown by force, and deſtroyed all the lawfull Heirs, ſhould ſay, none doth now pretend to the Crown, but my ſelf, and therefore un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly I have a true Title. I believe this is the firſt caſe, wherein a confident and peremptory claim, was ever thought to give a rightfull poſſeſſion.</p>
            <p>But I will no longer fight with a ſhadow, or purſue an Enemy, who hath a Bog for his retreat; for ſo I account all Arguments taken from <hi>unwritten Tradition;</hi> which is <hi>Bellarmine</hi>'s laſt refuge: for what can be more unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, than to alleadge <hi>old Stories,</hi> (which ſerve only to the advantage of the teller, and therefore may juſtly be ſuſpected to be forged by him) and to uſe them as Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, to perſwade us unto the belief of that, which in Reaſon is ridiculous; and in Scripture, the moſt authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick and allowed Tradition, is not ſo much as once menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned. The ſumme thereof of what I have to ſay is this; 1. It doth not appear, in any of the fore-mentioned pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that <hi>Peter</hi> had any peculiar Priviledge of <hi>Infallibility,</hi> or <hi>Authority</hi> granted to him, above the reſt of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles. 2. It doth much leſs appear that ever he was at <hi>Rome,</hi> or ſate as <hi>Biſhop</hi> there. 3. Upon ſuppoſition that the two firſt could be as clearly proved, as it is clear they cannot, yet that any of <hi>Peter</hi>'s perſonall Priviledges, ſhould be communicated to another, who will needs uſurp his Name, and ſtile himſelf his Succeſſour, can as little be maintained, as that his <hi>power of Miracles,</hi> his <hi>gift of Tongues,</hi> &amp;c. ſhould be continued, which the Pope as
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:50685:19"/>yet doth not pretend to. I conclude therefore, that <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi>'s firſt Plea from Scripture, is ſo far from Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, that it is ſcarce tolerable Sophiſtry, and ſo much in Anſwer to his firſt Argument.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>2</label> The ſecond Argument in defence of <hi>the Popes Infallibility,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bellar. <hi>de ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo Pontif. l.</hi> 4, 1</note> is taken from the <hi>Analogy and Reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance, that ought to be between the Jewiſh and the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Church. For in the Jewiſh Church,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bella, mine, there was an High Prieſt, which was Infallible; unto whom they were commanded to have recourſe, in all difficult Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and to abide by his Determination; as appears</hi> Deut. 17.8, 14. <hi>And therefore in the Chriſtian Church, there being the ſame, if not greater neceſſity, becauſe of the extent of it, it follows that there muſt likewiſe be ſome viſible Infallible Judge, for the ending of Controverſies, which will daily ariſe among Chriſtians, and this can be no other than the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this Argument from Analogy I anſwer;</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the ſimilitude and reſemblance between the Jewiſh and the Chriſtian Church, doth not conſiſt in ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the ſame outward Oeconomy, and Forms of Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration; as in a <hi>viſible High-Prieſt,</hi> with other Rites and Ordinances anſwerable to ſuch a Viſibility; but in the ſpirituall and inward performance, of what heretofore was materially and outwardly repreſented.
<note place="margin">He's 9.10.</note> So that the Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Sacrifices did not import, that they ſhould alwayes be continued, but, as the Apoſtle tells us, they were to laſt only, untill that great Sacrifice was offered, of which all the others were only faint and weak Preludiums. The like is declared concerning their <hi>meats</hi> and <hi>drinks,</hi> their <hi>waſhings,</hi> and <hi>bodily purifications,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 7.18.</note> with other <hi>carnall and on ſide Ordinances,</hi> which were only <hi>impoſed, untill the time of Reformation,</hi> and after that, were not, that we read of,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:50685:20"/>to be continued with new names, and under another form, but utterly to be aboliſhed,
<note place="margin">Heb. 7.18.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe of their weakneſs and unprofitableneſs.</hi> The like the Apoſtle obſerves concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>High Prieſt,</hi> into whoſe room our Saviour ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, who is called <hi>a Prieſt for ever,</hi> after another order than that of <hi>Aaron,</hi> even <hi>after the order of Melchiſedeck;</hi> who can ſupply all defects of his Church, without appointing a viſible Head in his place, by his own immediate Energy, <hi>ſince he lives for ever,
<note place="margin">Heb. 7.25.</note> to make interceſſion for them.</hi> So that if any upon earth now, will pretend to bear the ſame place in the Chriſtian Church, that <hi>Aaron</hi> did in the Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh, he muſt be able to ſhew the ſame divine warrant; for as the Apoſtle obſerves,
<note place="margin">Heb. 5.4, 5.</note> 
               <hi>No man takes this honour to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, but he that is called of God, as was Aaron; ſo alſo Chriſt did not glorify himſelf, to be an High Priſt, but he that ſaid to him thou art my Son this day I have begotten thee.</hi> Let then the Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> but deale above-board, and ſhow us ſome ſuch plaine place of Scripture, which doth Authorize his plea, and then let them be <hi>Anathema</hi> that will not ſubmit unto his Dictates; but ſince this is not ſo much as once offered, we cannot be faithfull to the Honour and Prerogative of out <hi>Great</hi> and <hi>only High Prieſt,</hi> if we doe not looke upon this pretended <hi>Vicar</hi> of his, as a bold and unwarrantable Intruder. But</p>
            <p n="2">2. It doth not appear, that the High Prieſt among the Jews, was at all Infallible, nor doth the place alleadged evince ſo much;
<note place="margin">Deut. 17.11.</note> for there <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpeaks not of Religious, but of civil cauſes; and commands that the Parties litigant, ſhould <hi>do according to the ſentence of the Law, which they ſhall teach thee;</hi> ſo that the High Prieſts were not to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce according to Tradition, or private fancy, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Law of God, which whoſo conſulted, might ſpeak Infallibly; not as if the High Prieſt, meerly by
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:50685:20"/>vertue of his Office and Place, was more priviledged from Errour, than the common Jew, but becauſe God did give his Law for an Infallible Rule, and in all parts that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned his own Worſhip, had made it ſo plain and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culat, that unleſs they would, they could not miſtake it. But for want of taking heed to it, we find that in <hi>David</hi>'s time, both himſelf and all the Prieſts did Erre, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving that the <hi>Arke</hi> might be carried <hi>upon a Cart,</hi> which was expreſſely commanded to be carried <hi>upon the Prieſts ſhoulders;</hi> whereupon when God ſmote <hi>Uzzah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Numb. 4.</note> 
               <hi>David</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged that a breach was made upon them,
<note place="margin">2 Chron 15.13</note> becauſe <hi>they ſought him not in the due order.</hi> Beſides in the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Apoſtacy of the people, which the Prophets ſo ſadly complain of, and ſo much enveigh againſt, we have no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to imagine,
<note place="margin">2 Reg 16.10.</note> that the High Prieſt continued ſtedfaſt in Religion; ſince in all probability, <hi>Uriah</hi> the <hi>Prieſt,</hi> whom <hi>Ahaz</hi> employed in building an <hi>Idolatrous Altar,</hi> was the <hi>Chief Priest</hi> at that time, and not only a <hi>partaker</hi> in, but a promoter of that wicked King's abominations. We read likewiſe, that none were more fierce againſt <hi>Jeremy,</hi> and other of Gods Prophets, than the Prieſts; and to put the matter out of Diſpute, we have it plainly told us, that there was for many ages, none in that Church that could Infallibly guid them; ſo the Pſalmiſt,
<note place="margin">Pſal: 74.9.</note> 
               <hi>We ſee not our Signs, there is no more any Prophets, neither is among us any that knoweth how long.</hi> And in <hi>Ezra</hi> we find, that the <hi>Tirſhatha,</hi> or Governour, as ſome think <hi>Nebemiah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezra 2.63.</note> commanded <hi>that they ſhould not eat of the moſt holy things, till there ſtood up a Prieſt with Urim and Thummim;</hi> who was to enquire of the Lord in difficult caſes, according to the command given to <hi>Joſhua,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Numb. 25.21.</note> that he ſhould conſult with <hi>Eleazar</hi> the Prieſt, who was to <hi>ask counſell for him, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the judgement of Urim:</hi> which in <hi>Ezra</hi>'s time,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:50685:21"/>was utterly ceaſed, and we do not read that ever it revived again. Juſt as much <hi>Infallibility</hi> therefore, as the <hi>High Prieſt</hi> and <hi>Sanhedrim</hi> had, in our Saviours time, when they put him to death; I am content to allow unto the <hi>Pope,</hi> and a <hi>Councell</hi> of his calling; and more than that, this Argument from Analogy will not amount to. For if they were ſo fatally deceived, in ſo important and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent a truth, who had, as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſuppoſeth, a clear promiſe of being Infallibly aſſiſted; how much more liable to Errour is the <hi>Biſhop of Rome,</hi> who hath no promiſe nor pretence of Plea, but only an uſurped and unjuſt poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Since then, 1. the High Prieſt of the Jewes, was only a Type of Chriſt, and did not figure any other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in the Chriſtian Church, who was to bear a Reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance to him: And 2. ſince he was not Infallible, but in the moſt concerning buſineſs that ever happened, and that was the acknowledgement of the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> moſt miſerably miſtaken: And laſtly, ſince the whole Argument doth no more concern the Infallibility of the <hi>Biſhop of Rome,</hi> than of any other Biſhop whatever; nothing can be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded from hence, but that the Propheſie of the Apoſtle, that God <hi>would give ſome up unto ſtrong deluſions, that they ſhould believe a lie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Theſ. 2 10.</note> by mens taking pains to urge ſuch kind of empty and frivolous Reaſonings as theſe, is abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly fulfilled. And ſo much in Anſwer to the ſecond Argument.</p>
            <p>The third and laſt Argument, to prove the <hi>Pope's In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibility,</hi> is taken <hi>from thoſe Inconveniences, which would follow in the Church of Chriſt, were there not ſome unerring Judge appointed, to determine Controverſies. For ſince our Saviour foretold, that there would be falſe Chriſts and falſe Prophets; ſince the Apoſtles tell us, that Hereſies and Errours would be vented; it would argue that our Saviour
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:50685:21"/>had ſmall care of his Church, ſhould be have left it without a Guide, unto whom all might have recourſe: As if a Maſter of a Ship, ſhould be at pains to rigge up a Veſſell, and put it to Sea, if he did not appoint a Pilot that might ſteer it through the Waves, and ſecure it from the Rocks, he might juſtly be taxed as very improvident. So</hi> ſaith <hi>Bellarmine, it will lay a great Imputation upon our Saviours Wiſedome, if, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt ſo many prodigious Errours, which, like Waves, are ready to overwhelm the Truth, he ſhould not have provided ſome ſuch known and viſible Pilot, who can guide the Ship of the Church, through all ſtorms, and preſerve it ſafe, from thoſe Rocks and Shelves, by ſtriking upon which, it is other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe liable to miſcarry. Some one therefore is requiſite to be the Judge of Controverſies, which by Confeſſion of all Ages, is no other but the</hi> Biſhop <hi>of</hi> Rome.</p>
            <p>I have enlarged this Argument, and put ſome kind of ſtouriſh upon it, becauſe this is indeed the Papiſts <hi>Achille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um;</hi> and upon all turns, the ſuppoſed Inconveniences, which will follow, if we admit not of their groundleſs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits, are alleadged to authorize their Unſcripturall In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions. Therefore I anſwer,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That Arguments drawn from Inconveniences, are ſo liable to miſtake and Errour, and, for the moſt part, do ſo much ſavour of Paſſion and Intereſt, as well as ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſightedneſs, in the Arguer; that, in all Diſputes, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Truth of any thing, they are of very little weight. It is no hard matter, to faſten ſome ſeeming Abſurdities, upon the moſt plain and clearly revealed Truth, as we know the <hi>Socinians</hi> do upon the Doctrine of the <hi>Trinity.</hi> The Jewes heretofore conceived our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our to be a <hi>Blaſphemer,</hi> and thought it would be very pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judiciall to their ſtate, to ſuffer him to live; and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards both <hi>Jewes</hi> and <hi>Romanes</hi> did agree, in ſtriving to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:50685:22"/>ſuppreſs his Doctrine, becauſe of ſome Politicall Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences, which they imagined would follow the ſpread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it. Yet all the while, our Saviour was really <hi>the Son of God,</hi> and his Doctrine, <hi>the Power of God unto Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation for all Believers.</hi> So that unleſs the Papiſts can clear to us, by ſome better Motives, than any they have yet produced, that their Biſhop is Infallible, the Inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences, which they ſuppoſe will follow our denying it, ought not to ſway with us.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Among Perſons, who own the Scriptures to be the Word of God, certainly it is much more rationall to ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue, ſuch a thing, (as for example the <hi>Popes Infallibility</hi>) is not once mentioned there, and therefore undoubtedly was never divinely appointed; than to ſay it is divinely appointed, becauſe otherwiſe it would be very Inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent. It would have been much more convenient, it all Mankind had been as Infallible, as the <hi>Pope</hi> is preſumed to be; if we had all retained our Innocence, and been ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted from Poſſibility of offending; one would think, this might have made more for the Honour of God, and the Peace of Mankind, than our preſent erring and ſinning Condition. But we muſt not meaſure Gods Appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or the Reall Being of things, by our own Rules of Convenience; nor affirm a Thing to be ſo, becauſe we conceive it would be very Convenient, if it were ſo. It is therefore but loſt labour, for the Popiſh Writers, in a great deal of Plauſible Language, to declare and ſet out the great Convenience of <hi>Infallibility,</hi> when they ſhould firſt prove to us the Truth and the Exiſtence of it. We may eaſily fancy, many things to be very Advantageous and Uſefull to the World, which yet never, either were, or will be: And amongſt theſe goodly <hi>Chimera's,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with fond perſons pleaſe themſelves; for ought I yet
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:50685:22"/>ſee, this Dream of <hi>Infallibility</hi> may claime a Chiefe place.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thoſe Terrible ſtories and Tragicall outcries, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the danger of <hi>Heriſies,</hi> for the ſuppreſſion of which, this expedient, of having ſome one <hi>Viſible Unerring Judge,</hi> muſt be found out; they are, for the moſt part, as Mr. <hi>Hales</hi> well obſerves, but <hi>ſo many Theologicall Scarecrowes, ſet up to fright us from the Diſquiſition and ſearch of Truth.</hi> I know very well, that to teach <hi>Hereſie</hi> i. e. any <hi>Falſe</hi> and <hi>Unchriſtian Doctrine,</hi> is a very great ſin; but yet, to prevent this, we muſt not in all haſte run into a greater:
<note place="margin">Supremum in Terris Numen &amp; Dominus Deus noſter Papa.</note> For to ſet up a <hi>viſible God upon Earth</hi> (according to the Court of Romes ſtile) to <hi>cry up a man,</hi> that is like our ſelves, to <hi>be Infallible;</hi> and then <hi>to fall down</hi> and <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him;</hi> to bring him for an offering, not thoſe worth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Creatures, as Sheep and Oxen (which onely were required of Old) but to Sacrifice our ſoules, to bind over our <hi>Reaſons</hi> and <hi>Underſtandings</hi> unto his <hi>Oracular Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates;</hi> this is ſo dull, ſo ſtupid an <hi>Idolatry,</hi> that we may wonder, any learned man would ever goe about to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend it, had not <hi>the God of this world blinded their eyes;</hi> and did they not <hi>by this Craft,</hi> as that Ancient Father <hi>Demetrius</hi> the <hi>Silver-Smith</hi> ſubtilty argued, <hi>get their Liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings;</hi> and divide the ſpoiles of the deluded world, by this groſſe and Palpable Cozenage.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, In anſwer to all their Allegations from <hi>Fathers</hi> and <hi>Authority,</hi> I need ſay no more than this, that as, though all the world did conſent to believe a <hi>Lie</hi> (as that <hi>the Sun was really no bigger then it ſeemes to be,</hi> which was the opinion of <hi>Epicurus</hi>) yet this Conſpiracy would never make a <hi>Lie</hi> to be <hi>Truth;</hi> ſo, upon ſuppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that all Antiquity did acknowledge this preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> yet could we not from thence
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:50685:23"/>inferre the Juſtice and the Legallity of it; becauſe the moſt that ſuch Teſtimonies amount to, is meerly this, to ſhow us, not what really was, but what they conceived to be True: I need not therefore be much concerned in examining <hi>Bellarmine</hi>'s Quotations. But yet that I may doe Juſtice to the Chriſtians of former Ages, and vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate them from being ſo Unwiſe, as the Pope's Champi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons would make us believe they were; I muſt affirme, that this Doctrine, is ſo farre from being owned by any of them, for many Centuries, that we have upon Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, many pregnant Inſtances, which doe evince that they did not ſo much as Dreame of it. To draw up which, I ſhall ſelect onely two or three famous Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, which <hi>Bellarmine</hi> is pleaſed to take no No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <note place="margin">Euſeb. <hi>l b.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 23, 24, 25.</note> The firſt Inſtance ſhall be from that doughty diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute which was raiſed about the yeare 160. concerning the day when <hi>Eaſter</hi> was to be kept, the Churches of <hi>Aſia</hi> kept <hi>Eaſter</hi>-day preciſely upon the 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of March; at which time the <hi>Jewes</hi> did ſolemnize their <hi>Paſſeover;</hi> but the <hi>Weſterne Churches.</hi> after many meetings to ſettle this weighty Controverſie, did agree that the day of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours Reſurrection, ſhould be celebrated onely upon the <hi>Lords Day.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> The <hi>Aſian Biſhops,</hi> notwithſtanding this Decree, did perſiſt in their former cuſtome, in which they were defended by <hi>Polycrates,</hi> who alleaged that <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip the Evangelist, John the Apoſtle</hi> and many others, did tranſmit that Traditionall Obſervance to them. Upon this, <hi>Victor</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> in great heat (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<note place="margin">Socrat <hi>lib.</hi> 6.</note> ſaith my Author) did take upon him to excommunicate all the <hi>Churches</hi> of <hi>Aſia,</hi> but being ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly writ againſt for it, and ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ffely oppoſed in it, he was forced to revoke his ſentence. Which ſtory might afford
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:50685:23"/>us very many Obſervations, as 1. That <hi>Superſtition</hi> and Needleſſe <hi>Obſervation of Dayes.</hi> 2. That <hi>Impoſition</hi> and <hi>Abridging of Chriſtian Liberty in things Indifferent.</hi> 3. That the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi>'s <hi>Uſurpation and exceeding the Bounds of his proper Juriſdiction,</hi> did begin to worke ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry early. But I wave theſe, and onely note, that had the <hi>Churches</hi> of <hi>Afia</hi> then thought the <hi>Biſhop of Rome</hi> to be <hi>Infallible,</hi> they would not ſo perempto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, in ſo ſmall a thing as the Retaining of an Old Cuſtome, have refuſed to ſubmit unto his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p n="2">2. My ſecond Inſtance ſhall be from that Controverſie, which for many yeares was very eagerly managed; <hi>viz. Whether ſuch as had received Baptiſme from Heretickes, upon their Returne to the Church,
<note place="margin">Cyprian. <hi>Epiſ.</hi> 92. <hi>Edit. Fam.</hi>
                  </note> ſhould be Baptized again or not? Cyprian</hi> and all the <hi>African Biſhops</hi> maintained the Neceſſiry of <hi>Re-baptizing;</hi> and in their Letter to <hi>Stephen</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> after they had at large given the Reaſons of their Opinion, they conclude, <hi>So much Dearest Brother, have we enformed you of, not doubting becauſe of the Truth of your</hi> Religion, <hi>but ſuch things will pleaſe you, which are both Religious and True. But yet we know, that ſome are very unwilling to lay down any Opinion, which they have once tooke up; but preſerving that mutuall agreement which ought to be amongſt Brethren, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the Cuſtomes which they have once been uſed to. In which matter, we neither Force nor give a Law to any; ſince in the ordering of the Church;
<note place="margin">Prapoſitus.</note> every Governour hath abſolute power of his own will, as being to give unto God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone a Reaſon of his Actings.</hi> From which paſſage writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by <hi>Cyprian</hi> and all the <hi>Biſhops of Africh</hi> (who mer together in a Councell for that purpoſe) it ſufficiently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares. 1. That they did not underſtand any thing of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:50685:24"/>the <hi>Biſhop of Rome</hi>'s <hi>Infallibility,</hi> ſince they profeſs to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain their own Judgement, without ſubſcribing to his. 2. That in the outward Regimen and Government of the Church, every Biſhop hath equall Power, and ought not Authoritatively, to preſcribe and impoſe Laws upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibid. Ep.</hi> 73.</note> As the ſame <hi>Cyprian,</hi> in another Letter; <hi>Theſe things,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>according to my weak Ability, have I writ, not Impoſing upon or Pre-judging any; as if it was not lawfull for every Biſhop to do as he thinks fit, ſince he hath free Power of his own Will.</hi> And afterwards, when <hi>Stephen</hi> had declared his Judgement, that he <hi>would have none baptized again, whatever Herefie they came from; but that the ancient Cuſtome ſhould be preſerved, whereby ſuch Converts were admitted into Church Communion, meerly by laying on of Hands.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid. Ep.</hi> 74. <hi>Inter catera vel ſuperba, vel ad rem non perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nentia, vel ſibi ipſi contraria, quae improvidè at<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> imperitè ſcripſit.</hi>
                  </note> Cyprian,</hi> in ſtead of yeelding to his Determination, doth taxe his Letter of <hi>Pride, Folly,</hi> and <hi>Impertinence;</hi> and, in Anſwer to thoſe words of his, wherein <hi>Stephen</hi> commanded that nothing ſhould be vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, from the accuſtomed Tradition; <hi>Whence,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>was that Tradition? Did it deſcend from the Authority of our Lord and his Goſpel? Did it come from the Commands and Epiſtles of the Apoſtles? For God teſtifies in his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, both to Joſhua and others, that</hi> thoſe things only ſhould be done which were written. <hi>And our Lord Chriſt, when he ſent his Apoſtles into the World, commands them</hi> to Baptize, and to Teach all Nations, that they might ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve and do all things, which he had Commanded. <hi>If therefore any ſuch Cuſtome,</hi> (meaning that of <hi>Stephen</hi>'s) <hi>be contained, either in the Goſpels, or in the Epiſtles and Acts of the Apoſtles, then let ſach an Holy and Divine Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition be obſerved. But what Obſtinacy, what Preſumption is it, to prefer</hi> Humane Tradition, <hi>before a Divine Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment? What Folly is it not to conſider, that God is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:50685:24"/>as often as</hi> Humane Tradition <hi>doth leſſen and diſcoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance Divine Precepts; as he teſtifies by the Prophet Iſay? And our Saviour likewiſe, in his Goſpel, rebuking and chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Phariſees,</hi> Ye reject the Commands of God, that ye may keep your own Tradition. <hi>Of which words, the Apoſtle Paul being mindfull, he likewiſe adviſeth and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructeth us,</hi> ſaying, If any man teach otherwiſe, and reſte not in the ſound words of our Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and in his Doctrine; he is puffed up, knowing nothing; from ſuch turn aſide. <hi>Neither ought</hi> Cuſtome, <hi>which hath pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vily crept in amongst ſome, to hinder</hi> Truth <hi>from prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. For</hi> Cuſtome, <hi>without</hi> Truth;
<note place="margin">Conſuetudo ſine veritate vetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtas Erroris eſt.</note> 
               <hi>is nothing elſe but the</hi> Antiquity of Errour. <hi>And it ariſeth only from Pride and Preſumption, that one is apt to defend his own Practices, how Falſe and erroneous ſoever, rather than conſent to that, which is True and Right in another. For which reaſon, the Apoſtle</hi> Paul <hi>writing to</hi> Timothy,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Docibilem Gr.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>adviſeth a Biſhop</hi> not to be Contentious, but Meek and Apt to Teach. <hi>But he is</hi> Apt to Teach, <hi>who is Gentle, and endued with Patience to Learn: for a Biſhop ought not only to Teach, but to Learn; ſince he Teacheth beſt, who continually grows and profits by Learning. Which the Apoſtle</hi> Paul <hi>likewiſe declares, when he admoniſheth,</hi> That if any thing be revealed to another which ſits by, the Firſt ſhould hold his Peace. <hi>Religious and ſincere Minds are alwayes prepared to lay aſide Errour, and to ſearch for Truth; for if we return unto the Head and Originall of</hi> Divine Tradition, <hi>Hamane Errour ceaſeth; and when the Reaſon of the Heavenly Appointments, is once throughly diſcerned, whatever lay hid in Obſcurity, is clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up, and brought to Light. As if a Pipe, that formerly conveyed a great Quantity of Water, ſhould ſuddenly fail; we would the a have recourſe unto the Fountain, to learn the true Conſe of ſuch a Stop and Interciſion, that if the fault
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:50685:25"/>was in the Pipe, it might be repaited, and fitted to receive the Streams of Water, in the ſame Abundance and Purity, that they iſſue from the Fountain: ſo likewiſe ought all the Miniſters of God, in their Obſervance of Divine Commands, to do: that if the Truth ſeems wavering and uncertain in any Point,
<note place="margin">Ad Originem Dominicam, &amp; Evangelicam, &amp; Apoſtolicam Traditionem.</note> we may have recourſe unto the Originall,</hi> to wit, <hi>the Tradition of our Lord, in his Goſpel, and by his Apoſtles: that ſo the Ground of our Acting may proceed thence, whence the Order and Originall of it did firſt ariſe.</hi> I have at large quoted theſe words out of <hi>Cyprian,</hi> both to ſhew how lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle the <hi>Biſhop of Rome</hi>'s Authority was then valued; and likewiſe to manifeſt, what that Holy and Learned Man thought to be the only way, whereby all Controverſies in Religion ought to be decided: not to depend upon <hi>Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain Traditions,</hi> which at the beſt are but the Inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Men; but to have Immediate recourſe unto the Scriptures, and to go no further in any part of Divine Worſhip, than as their Rule doth guid us. And this Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of his, the Papiſts cannot in Juſtice refuſe, ſince <hi>Cyprian</hi> is a <hi>Saint</hi> in their Calender, and yet died without ever retracting his Judgement.</p>
            <p n="3">3. My Third and Laſt Inſtance ſhall be, that notable Speech of Pope <hi>Gregory,</hi> about ſix hundred years after our Saviours time; who having had great conteſts for Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riority, with <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Patriarch of Conſtantinople;</hi> when at ſaſt, <hi>John,</hi> having the Emperour on his ſide, did en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to gain the Title of <hi>Univerſall Biſhop,
<note place="margin">Greg. <hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>Ep.</hi> 32, 33.</note> Gregory</hi> did fiercely oppoſe him in it, and in many of his Epiſtles, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms that whoever ſhould Aſſume that Stile, he was the <hi>Forerunner of Antichriſt, a Child of the Devil, an Apostate from the Faith;</hi> with many other ſharp, but true, ſayings to the ſame Purpoſe. It pleaſed God that within few years after, <hi>An.</hi> 606, Pope <hi>Boniface,</hi> little minding the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:50685:25"/>Predictions of his Predeceſſour, did not only claim, but likewiſe actually take to himſelf that Name, which, as a Badge of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> and an <hi>Infallible Mark</hi> to know him by, he hath ever ſince tranſmitted to his Succeſſours. Now I ask, whether Pope <hi>Gregory,</hi> was Infallible in that Opinion of his, which he doth ſo often, and ſo earneſtly inſiſt upon? If they tell me he was, then we need not diſpute any farther, <hi>Whether the Pope be Antichriſt,</hi> for we have <hi>Gregorie</hi>'s own Confeſſion, that whoever would arrogate to himſelf, the Name of <hi>Univerſall Biſhop,</hi> was undoubtedly ſo; but, if they ſay, he was not, then their Conceit of <hi>Infallibility</hi> vaniſheth, as amounting to no more than this, that the Pope is <hi>Infallible,</hi> when he Speaks and Acts, for the Advantage of his See; but very <hi>Fallible</hi> when he ſpeaks any thing, though never ſo deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berately, which in after Ages may make againſt it.</p>
            <p>I have forebore to Urge, that many of the <hi>Popes</hi> have actually fallen into <hi>Hereſie,</hi> as <hi>Honorius,</hi> by Name, who by the ſixth <hi>Synod,</hi> was condemned for an Heretick, and his Epiſtles commanded to be burnt; and the very ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs words of ſome of their Canons are, <hi>That the Pope cannot be judged by any, unleſs he be found to have crred from the Faith;</hi> which doth ſuppoſe, even in the Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his own Canoniſts, that there is a Poſſibility of his Erring. Neither do I inſiſt upon the Decrees of the Councels of <hi>Baſil</hi> and <hi>Conſtance,</hi> which were both aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, for the depoſing of two Popes that were unduely Choſen; and in them it was Enacted, that <hi>A Councell was above the Pope,</hi> which they ſtrictly command all to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve as an <hi>Article of Faith:</hi> Which Inſtances, though they ſtrike ſufficiently at the Pope's <hi>Infallibility,</hi> and <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramount Authority,</hi> yet becauſe the Anſwer of ſome of the moſt Moderate and Ingenuous Papiſts, is, that <hi>Though the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:50685:26"/>Pope be not Infallible in himſelf, yet in and with a Councell, he is.</hi> I ſhall therefore ſpeak a little to this Conceit; and then conclude.</p>
            <p>I demand therefore of thoſe, who maintain the <hi>Infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of the Pope, and a Councell conjunctim;</hi> what Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Warrant have they for ſuch an Opinion? and where hath God promiſed Infallible Aſſiſtance, unto a <hi>Councell</hi> of the Pope's Calling? For thoſe Texts, that are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly made uſe of, as <hi>Hear the Church;</hi> and, <hi>The Spirit ſhall lead you into all Truth;</hi> and, <hi>It ſeemed good unto the Holy Ghoſt, and to us;</hi> with ſome few others to the ſame ſenſe, are as impertinently alleadged in behalf of a <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell,</hi> as thoſe fore-mentioned, are in behalf of the <hi>Pope.</hi> For</p>
            <p n="1">1. That Command, <hi>Tell the Church,</hi> doth not ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie an Appeal unto a Synod of Biſhops,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at. 18.</note> (who are all of the Pope's Creation, and therefore muſt needs be Partiall for him) but <hi>Church</hi> there ſignifies, that <hi>particular Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> to which we relate as Members; neither do our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour's words concern <hi>Articles of Faith,</hi> and Matters of Opinion, but meerly <hi>Civil Injuries,</hi> as is plain from the Context; for our Saviour having commanded them <hi>to forgive one another,</hi> he then goes on to tell them, what courſe they ſhould take, in caſe a Brother ſhould offend them; firſt, <hi>to reprove him privately;</hi> and if that prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not, then <hi>to take two or three,</hi> as witneſſes of their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings: But if notwithſtanding this, the Injurious Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſtill continued Obſtinate, then to tell it <hi>Caetui,</hi> or <hi>to the Congregation;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 5.</note> as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> adviſeth the <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> that <hi>being all met together, they ſhould proceed to cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 5.20.</note> and to <hi>Timothy, Them that ſin, rebuke before all,</hi> i. e. all of that Church, or Congregation, to which they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long, <hi>that others alſo may fear.</hi> And this ſenſe, beſides
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:50685:26"/>that it is the proper meaning of the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>or Church,</hi> (which often in Scripture ſignifies the <hi>Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> diſtinct from their <hi>Officers;</hi> but never the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry) it likewiſe fully agrees with our Saviours Scope, who, as the Offence ariſeth, would have the Remedy to ariſe proportionably, and therefore he uſeth this Gradati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that firſt <hi>one</hi> ſhould reprove an Offending Brother, then <hi>two or three,</hi> then the <hi>Church, or more;</hi> according to what we find practiſed in the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> who it ſeems had agreed to cenſure the <hi>Inceſtuous Perſon,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as the Apoſtle had commanded them,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 2.9.</note> and therefore he tells them, <hi>Sufficient to ſuch a one is the Reprehenſion by many,</hi> i. e. even by all the Members of that <hi>Chriſtian Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly,</hi> to which he did relate; and if the Offender would not hearken to them, then he was to be thrown out of Communion, and to be accounted as a Stranger to the <hi>Church;</hi> even as an <hi>Heathen, and a Publican.</hi> And ſuch Determinations of every particular Church, our Saviour ſaith, ſhould be ratified in Heaven; <hi>For,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>where two or three</hi> (not Biſhops, but Believers) <hi>are gathered together in my Name, there I will be in the midſt of them:</hi> i. e. When any Number of Believers, how ſmall ſoever, though but <hi>two or three,</hi> are met for thoſe Holy Ends of Diſcipline, and in thoſe Ways, which I by my Commands have warranted, I will be with them to Aſſiſt and to Guide their Councels, and to Execute their Sentence.
<note place="margin">Chap. 49.</note> Accordingly we find in <hi>Tertullian</hi>'s <hi>Apology,</hi> that in all Chriſtian Meetings upon the Lords-day, together with <hi>Prayer</hi> and <hi>Preaching,</hi> there was likewiſe <hi>Cenſura Divina;</hi> i. e. the <hi>Sentence of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication,</hi> pronounced againſt all refractory and ſtubborn Sinners: according to this, our Saviours Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>If any object, that <hi>if Chriſt will be with two or three,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:50685:27"/>then in all probabily he will be with a Councell of many Hundreds, much more.</hi> I anſwer, No doubt he will, <hi>if they meet in his Name</hi> i. e. according to his Command and Inſtitution; for it is not the Aſſembly, though, of never ſo many Thouſands, but the End and Manner of Aſſembling, which hath the Promiſe of Aſſiſtance. And when I can ſee ſuch a <hi>Councell,</hi> which profeſſeth ſolely to follow Scripture, according to that ſenſe which (not the fancy of men, whether <hi>Fathers</hi> or <hi>Councells,</hi> but) the <hi>Spirit of God</hi> enlightning their underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, doth give unto it; I ſhall then with all Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence embrace their <hi>Decrees.</hi> For I know that ſuch a <hi>Councell cannot Erre,</hi> becauſe they will Command no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but what is already commanded by God; which every true Chriſtian ought to obey, without the Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of any other Authority. But ſuch a <hi>Councell</hi> as this, I am hopeleſſe of ever ſeeing under the <hi>Pape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy;</hi> ſince all their meetings, for ſome hundreds of Yeares, have been deſigned, not to <hi>ſearch</hi> but, to <hi>ſmother</hi> Scripture; and to Empriſon that <hi>Light,</hi> which if looked into, would detect and manifeſt their Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors. So that they come together, not in <hi>Chriſts</hi> but; in the <hi>Pope</hi>'s <hi>name;</hi> or rather <hi>in the name of that God of the world, who is Prince of the Power of Darkneſſe;</hi> and whoſe <hi>Kingdome</hi> is founded and upheld by the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifice and cunning of their Teachers, and by the Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and <hi>Implicite Faith</hi> of their Hearers. <hi>Fallere &amp; Falli To deceive and to be deceived,</hi> is the beſt Motto which can be ſet upon all the Church-doores in the Papall Territories; but <hi>Heaven</hi> is a place of <hi>Light,</hi> and the True Church is full of Knowledge, becauſe <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> are all taught of God,</hi> not to obey or to Believe in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, but in him alone.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb facs="tcp:50685:27"/> 2. That Promiſe of our Saviour, <hi>I will ſend the Spirit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">John. 14. &amp;c. 16.</note> 
               <hi>which ſhall lead you into all Truth,</hi> was ſpoken Perſonally to the Apoſtles: And thoſe words,
<note place="margin">Act. 15.</note> 
               <hi>It ſeemeth good to the Holy Spirit and to Us,</hi> were ſpoken by them, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the accompliſhment of that Promiſe; ſo that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out great preſumption, they cannot be wreſted to any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; nor ſuch wreſting, without great vanity, be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed: ſince barely to deny ungrounded ſuppoſitions, is a ſufficient Confutation.</p>
            <p>If any aske me, ſince <hi>neither the Pope nor a Councell is Infallible,</hi> as having no peculiar Promiſe for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, then <hi>how ſhall the Church determine Controverſies,</hi> or, <hi>How ſhall Hereſies be ſuppreſſed?</hi> I anſwer, that if the word of God is clear, and the <hi>Hereſie</hi> be Notorious; than every Particular Church hath Power within it ſelf, to <hi>excommunicate</hi> all obſtinate Heretickes. But, where the Scripture, is either Dubious or Silent,
<note place="margin">Phil. 3.15.</note> there charitably to beare with diſſenters, and to wait till <hi>God ſhall reveale it to them,</hi> is the beſt way to winne them. And this was the onely method, which the primitive Chriſtians did take for three hundred yeares together, to preſerve and maintaine the Truth of our Religion. <hi>Having no Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion</hi> with ſuch, as hold manifeſt and deſtructive Errors; and in things of leſſer moment, <hi>Forbearing one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother in Love;</hi> Theſe will at laſt be found to be the ſafe <hi>wayes of God;</hi> whereas to pretend to <hi>Infallibility in determining,</hi> or to practiſe <hi>Tyranny in Impoſing,</hi> theſe are onely the wayes of Ambitious and ſelf-ſeeking men, found out not ſo much to promote Truth (which ſtands not in need of ſuch Arts) as to Augment a party; which makes all <hi>Articles of Faith,</hi> to be meerly like the <hi>Civill Lawes</hi> of a Land, where moſt Voices doe carry the Cauſe. Such a kind of <hi>Univerſality</hi> as this, True
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:50685:28"/>
               <hi>Piety</hi> never had, and therefore we need not be ſorry, that <hi>Popery</hi> doth make its boaſt of it.</p>
            <p>And thus I have, with as much Brevity and Plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, as the ſubject would beare, enquired into the Grounds, whereupon the <hi>Popes Infallibility</hi> is ſaid to be grounded, and after the moſt Impartiall ſearch, can pronounce of them all <hi>Mene Tekell</hi> that being <hi>weighed in the Balance of the Sanctuary, they are found too light.</hi> Neither have I diverted my ſelf, in confuting their <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of Images,</hi> their Blaſphemous Figment <hi>of Tranſſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation,</hi> their mingling of <hi>works</hi> in <hi>Juſtification,</hi> their <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation of Angells,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 2.19.</note> which the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>is not to hold the Head,</hi> i. e. <hi>to Erre fundamentally.</hi> Their <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding of Marriage and commanding to abſtain from meats.</hi> Which he who propheſied of them,
<note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.1.</note> calls the <hi>Doctrine of Devils.</hi> I have omitted likwiſe their Furious and Bloody Tenets of Perſecuting and Killing all, <hi>who doe not worſhip the Image of that Beaſt</hi> which they have e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected;
<note place="margin">Rev. 13.15.</note> for theſe things, how plainely ſoever the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſpeakes againſt them, will not much concerne them to anſwer, as long as they are fenced about with the <hi>Doctrine of Infallibility;</hi> whereby they are privileged to put what ſenſe upon Scripture they pleaſe: but if the Chriſtian Reader finds that conceit to be clearly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, then I hope he will make uſe of the other Arguments, to ſatisfie himſelf, that we have but too much reaſon to ſuſpect the <hi>Pope to be that Antichriſt, that</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <hi>Lawleſſe one, who ſits in the Temple of God, and declares that he is God:</hi> For <hi>in the Church,</hi> which is the <hi>Temple</hi> or <hi>Houſe of God;</hi> for any man to make Lawes, which doe oblige the Conſcience; For a <hi>ſinfull</hi> man to ſtile himſelf <hi>the Head and Bridegroome of the Church,</hi> and above all, to affirme that he is <hi>Infallible,</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:50685:28"/>this is nothing elſe but to ſay that he is <hi>God;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in to fulfill the moſt clear Prediction that can be, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>The Man of ſin;</hi> whoſe way of Riſing was to be, by the <hi>Deceiveableneſſe of Unrighteouſneſſe,</hi> and his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion to be Eſtabliſhed by <hi>Miracles and Lying Wonders;</hi> Which no Church in the world doth more confidently boaſt of than the <hi>Roman.</hi> And therefore till her un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy and much miſtaken Followers have cleared, that She is not <hi>Antichriſtian,</hi> we have little reaſon to believe that She is a <hi>True Church;</hi> much leſſe, to think that She is <hi>Infallible.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
